A Guide to the Papers of John Casey
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10973
Papers of John Casey 1939-1990
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10973
ca. 1700 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Photocopying is restricted except by written permission of Mr. Casey.
Acquisition Information
This collection was loaned to the library on August 22, 1990.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of American writer John Dudley Casey(1939-), 7.5 linear feet, ca. 1700 items, 22 Hollinger boxes, 1939-1990, containing John Casey's juvenilia; correspondence; manuscripts of his magazine articles and book reviews; manuscripts of his short stories and novellas; manuscripts of his novels, An American Romance, Everyman's Dream, Monticello and People's Drug Store, Spartina, and Testimony and Demeanor; and cassette tapes of his interviews and readings.
Casey was educated at Harvard College (B.A. cum laude 1962), Harvard Law School (L.L.B. 1965), and the University of Iowa (M.F.A. 1968). He has taught at the University of Iowa Law School, the University of Rhode Island, Randolph-Macon Women's College, and the University of Virginia. Casey's awards include a Guggenheim Fellowship (1979-1980), a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship (1982), the O. Henry Award (1988), and the National Book Award (1989). Casey's published works include the books An American Romance (1977), Testimony and Demeanor (1979), and Spartina (1989); short stories in The New Yorker (1968-1988), Chicago Magazine (1983), Ploughshares (1981), Redbook (1972), and Sports Illustrated (1969); book reviews; and magazine articles.
The collection is organized into five series: topical and miscellaneous personal papers, including autobiographical materials, juvenilia, college essays and other work, teaching notes and evaluations, and students' stories; correspondence, separated by subject and correspondent, with separate folders for more widely-known writers, and including alphabetized miscellaneous letters; manuscripts of book reviews and magazine articles, short stories, and novels; sound recordings of Casey's readings and interviews; and two items, a manuscript of the story "A Political Primer" and an author's proof of the story "Avid," in oversize folders.
The organization of the collection groups the novella "A Year in Mid-Air" (Redbook, 1972) with the short stories, and the story collection Testimony and Demeanor (1979) with the novels.
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence re Employment, 1967-1969, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence re Book Publishing, 1967-1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence re Magazine Publishing, 1965-1988, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters of Congratulation, 1968-1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Other Authors, 1968-1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Ann Arensberg, 1980,1986 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from the Barnes Family, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Elizabeth Benedict(formerly Elizabeth Neidetz), 1978-1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Letter from Vance Bourjaily, 1978 (Box Box 1)
  - Letter from T. Alan Broughton, 1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Rosamond Pittman Casey, 1980, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Jane Barnes Caseyand Maudand Nell Casey, 1979-1989, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from the Casey Family, 1966-1989 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Susan Heeger, 1978-1989 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from John Irving, 1968, 1977-1988 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Peter Janet, 1978, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Richard Jones, 1977-1989 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Steve Jones, 1977-1988 (Box Box 1)
  - Letter from Jim MacPherson, 1980 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Jonathan Penner, 1979, 1990 (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from David Plimpton, 1968, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Peter Taylor, (1965-1968)1980, n.d. (Box Box 1)
  - Letters from Kurt Vonnegut, Jr., 1967-1971 (Box Box 2)
  - Letters from Richard Wertime, 1980 (Box Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1966-1990, n.d.; (2 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Topical and Miscellaneous
  - Autobiographical Materials, [1988], n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Awards and Speech Notes, 1964, 1989, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - Childhood Correspondence and Papers, 1939-1952, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - College Essays, n.d. (Box Box 2)
  - School Records and Related Correspondence, 1947-1956 (Box Box 2)
  - Photographs and Stamps (Box Box 3)
  - Poetry, 1960, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Students' Stories, 1978, 1988, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Teaching Notes, n.d. (Box Box 3)
  - Travel Diary: Russia, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Manuscripts
  - Manuscripts: Articles and Book Reviews
    - Arkansas National Bass Fishing Tournamentarticle, n.d. (Box Box 3)
    - Book Reviews, n.d. (Box Box 3)
    - Cross-Country Ski article, n.d. (Box Box 3)
    - "In Praise of Womens' Muscles", 1978-1980 (Box Box 3)
    - Interview of Kurt Vonnegut, n.d. (Box Box 3)
    - Kindly Lights foreword (Box Box 3)
    - Memorial Essays, 1977-1983 (Box Box 3)
    - Rowing article, n.d. (Box Box 4)
    - "The Social Life of the Long-Distance Runner", 1969 (Box Box 4)
    - Sports: Research Clippings, 1973, 1976, n.d. (Box Box 4)
    - Sports Writings, n.d. (Box Box 4)
    - The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake afterword, n.d. (Box Box 4)
    - "Tom Brown, Tracker", 1982-1983 (Box Box 4)
    - "The Watch that Ends the Night", 1969; (2 folders) (Box Box 4)
  - Manuscripts: Short Stories
    - "Avid," with autograph revisions by the author, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 4)
    - "Avid", n.d.; Ams, Tms (Box Box 4)
    - "Avid," notes, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 4)
    - "Avid" (2 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Avid: Revised Version", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Avid," with comments by others (2 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Avid," with publication copy, 1988; galley proofs (Box Box 5)
    - "Bobbie Booth", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Connaissance des Arts" (2 folders), n.d.; AMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Connaissance des Arts," originally titled "Lapses", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Connaissance des Arts", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 5)
    - "Connaissance des Arts", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 6)
    - "Connaissance des Arts", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 6)
    - "Connaissance des Arts," notes, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 6)
    - "Conspirators," with autograph revisions by the author, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 6)
    - "Conspirators" (3 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 6)
    - "The Fisherman and His Wife", AMs, TMs (Box Box 6)
    - "Home Again, Home Again", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 6)
    - "Mandarins in a Farther Field," with published copy, 1969; AMs (Box Box 6)
    - "A More Complete Cross-Section", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 7)
    - "My Last Captain", 1965; TMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Peter Downing", n.d.; AMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Rapunzel", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 7)
    - Rhode Island cycle (Volume I) notes, AMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Sleeping Beauty", n.d.; AMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Sleeping Beauty", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Smythe", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Smythe," notes, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Snow White", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Snow White", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 7)
    - "Snow White," with publication copy, 1983, n.d.; galley proofs (Box Box 7)
    - "Starry Night", n.d.; AMs, TMS (Box Box 8)
    - "Starry Night" (2 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 8)
    - "Supper at the Black Pearl", n.d.; AMs (Box Box 8)
    - "Supper at the Black Pearl", n.d.; TMs (Box Box 8)
    - "Testimony and Demeanor", AMs (Box Box 8)
    - "Testimony and Demeanor," with publication copy, 1971; galley proofs (Box Box 8)
    - "The Use of Her Estate", n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 8)
    - "A Year in Mid-Air," under earlier title, AMs (Box Box 8)
    - "A Year in Mid-Air," with galley proofs and publication copy, 1972, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 8)
    - "A Year in Mid-Air," draft as notes for a screenplay based on the author's novella, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 8)
    - untitled story, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 9)
    - Washington story notes, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 9)
    - Washington story fragments (2 folders), n.d.; AMs (Box Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous untitled stories, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 9)
    - Story fragments (2 folders), n.d.; AMs (Box Box 9)
    - Story fragments in Harvard notebook, 1964; AMs (Box Box 10)
    - Story fragments in notebooks, 1964, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 10)
    - Notebooks and inserts (3 folders), 1960, 1962, n.d.; AMs (Box Box 10)
  - Manuscripts: Novels
    - An American Romance, early draft (partially incomplete) with autograph revisions by the author (5 folders), n.d.; AMs (Box Box 11)
    - An American Romance, draft with extensive autograph revisions by the author (2 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 11)
    - An American Romance, draft with extensive autograph revisions by the author (3 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 12)
    - An American Romance draft (5 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 12)
    - An American Romance draft (2 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 13)
    - An American Romance publication copy (3 folders), [1970's]; TMs (EC) (Box Box 13)
    - An American Romance publication copy, [1970's]; TMs (EC) (Box Box 14)
    - An American Romance, proofs with holograph corrections by the editor, 1977; galley proofs (Box Box 14)
    - An American Romance, 1977; galley proofs (Box Box 14)
    - An American Romance, 1977; page proofs (Box Box 14)
    - An American Romance, synopsis for a film version of the author's novel, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 14)
    - An American Romance, loose notes and text excerpts marked "throwaway pages" by the author, AMs, TMs (Box Box 14)
    - An American Romance, notes, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 15)
    - An American Romance, notes and text fragments in notebook pads, AMs (Box Box 15)
    - An American Romance, editor's comments and author's synopses, AMs, TMs (Box Box 15)
    - An American Romance, 1977-1979; reviews (Box Box 15)
    - Everyman's Dream, early draft with extensive autograph revisions by the author (2 folders), [1960's]; AMs (Box Box 15)
    - Everyman's Dream, early draft with autograoph revisions by the author, [1960's]; AMs (Box Box 15)
    - Everyman's Dream, marked "Novel-in-Progress," written while at Iowa Creative Writing Workshop, [1960's]; TMs (mimeo) (Box Box 15)
    - Everyman's Dream, [1960's]; TMs (Box Box 16)
    - Everyman's Dream, draft with autograph revisions by the author, [1960's]; AMs (Box Box 16)
    - Everyman's Dream, draft of AMs in previous folder, [1960's]; TMs (Box Box 16)
    - Everyman's Dream, [1960's]; TMs (Box Box 16)
    - Everyman's Dream (3 folders), [1960's]; TMs (Box Box 16)
    - Everyman's Dream, draft with autograph revisions by the author, [1960's]; TMs (Box Box 16)
    - Everyman's Dream, draft with autograph revisions by the author, [1960's]; TMs (Box Box 17)
    - Everyman's Dream, narrative fragments, [1960's]; AMs, TMs (Box Box 17)
    - Everyman's Dream, notes, [1960's]; AMs (Box Box 17)
    - Monticello and People's Drug Store, notes and narrative fragments, AMs (Box Box 17)
    - Monticello and People's Drug Store, draft in spiral- bound notebook tablets, AMs (Box Box 17)
    - Spartina, draft segments in notepads (4 folders), n.d.; AMs (Box Box 18)
    - Spartina, draft of opening chapters, with autograph revisions by the author, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 18)
    - Spartina, draft segments with autograph revisions by the author (2 folders), n.d.; AMs (Box Box 18)
    - Spartina, draft with autograph revisions by the author and others, TMs (Box Box 18)
    - Spartina, draft with autograph revisions by the author and others (2 folders), TMs (Box Box 19)
    - Spartina (2 folders), n.d.; TMs (Box Box 19)
    - Spartina, setting copy with printer's notes (2 folders), 1989; TMs (Box Box 19)
    - Spartina, setting copy with printer's notes (3 folders), 1989; TMs (Box Box 20)
    - Spartina, final draft (2 folders), 1989; TMs(ec) (Box Box 20)
    - Spartina, research materials: clippings, notes, n.d. (Box Box 20)
    - Spartina, revision notes, n.d.; AMs, TMs (Box Box 20)
    - Spartina, loose pages from a draft, n.d.; TMs (Box Box 20)
    - Spartina, notes and text fragments, AMs (Box Box 20)
    - Spartina, notes and text fragments, AMs (Box Box 21)
    - Spartina, advertisements and posters, 1989 (Box Box 21)
    - Spartina, notes and itineraries for the author's post-publication book tour, 1989, 1990 (Box Box 21)
    - Spartina, 1989, 1990; reviews (Box Box 21)
    - Volume III/ Elsie's Novel, [1980s]; AMs (Box Box 21)
    - Volume III/ Elsie's Novel, draft with autograph revisions by the author, [1980s]; AMs (Box Box 21)
    - Volume III/ Elsie's Novel, draft with autograph revisions by the author, [1980s]; TMs (Box Box 21)
    - Volume III/ Elsie's Novel (2 folders), [1980s]; TMs (Box Box 22)
    - Testimony and Demeanor, draft with autograph revisions by the author, TMs (Box Box 22)
    - Testimony and Demeanor (2 folders), TMs (Box Box 22)
    - Testimony and Demeanor, loose pages, TMs (Box Box 22)
    - Testimony and Demeanor, 1980; Galley Proofs (Box Box 22)
    - Testimony and Demeanor, 1979, n.d.; reviews (Box Box 22)
- Sound Recordings
  - Interview with Kurt Vonnegut, [1960s]; T-907; (3 cassettes: a,b,c)
  - "Nightscope" with Barry Burnsen, episode on Iowa Citybarhopping which includes a recording of John Casey(masquerading as an Irishman) telling fictitious drinking stories, [1960s]; T-908; (1 reel-to-reel tape)
  - "FM Insights: John Casey's 'The Fisherman and his wife'": Casey reads the title story for a WTJU(University of Virginia student radio) reading series, 1981; T-909; (1 cassette)
  - "N. Adams w/ John Casey": interview with John Casey about Breece D'J Pancake, 1983; T-910; (1 cassette)
  - "Virginia Writers II / Program #7: Walter Norris": Ben Clearyinterviews Walter Norris, an author from Virginia's Northern Neck, for a public radio series, n.d.; T-911; (1 cassette)
  - "Virginia Writers II / Program #11: John Casey": Ben Clearyinterviews John Casey for a public radio series, n.d.; T-912; (1 cassette)
- Oversize Materials
  - "Avid," proof with inserts and autograph revisions by the author and a reader, 1987; author's proof (Box Oversize)
  - "A Political Primer," draft with autograph revisions by the author, n.d.; AMs (Box Oversize)